Catharine C. M. Edes Papers, 1822-1856
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Catharine May Edes Papers
1822-1856
1849-1852
Edes, Catharine May, 1782-
MS 54
1 box (.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Traveler. When Edes was in her late sixties, she traveled through Europe during wartime with her sister. Papers consist of correspondence and journals. Written during her time in Europe, mostly from England, letters include descriptions of art; landmarks; life and war in Europe; the 1849 cholera epidemic in London; Sontag and Madame Alboni performing at the Birmingham Musical Festival; the Congress of Princes in Berlin; Jenny Lind singing in Stockholm; and the marriage of Prince Carl to the Princess of Holland in Upsala.
Biographical Note
Catharine Cravath May Edes was born in 1782. She lived in Boston, Massachusetts with her extended family, the Mays. From 1849 to 1852, when Edes was in her late sixties, she travelled through Europe during wartime with her sister Sophie Tuckerman. Little else is known of Catharine Edes' life. She wrote her will in January 1844 and produced an account book of her estate in 1856.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Catharine C.M. Edes Papers consist of 2.5 linear inches including correspondence and 130 pages of journal entries written from August 1849 to August 1852. Letters to her family were written during her time in Europe, mostly from England. Edes wrote of the 1849 cholera epidemic in London and of hearing Sontag and Madame Alboni perform at the Birmingham Musical Festival. She and her sister heard Jenny Lind sing in Stockholm before her departure to tour America, and were in Upsala for the marriage of Prince Carl to the Princess of Holland. Many of the letters mention the war activities in Europe and the "armies moving in all directions." The collection also includes Edes' passport, a book of pressed flowers, her will, and an account book. There is one folder of letters written by Edes' sister, Sophie Tuckerman.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The Catharine C.M. Edes Papers were presented by Margaret Roys, through the introduction of Grace P. Fuller (Smith 1903).
Search Terms
Edes, Catharine May, 1782-; Europe--Description and travel--Sources; Europe--Social life and customs--19th century--Sources; May family; Tuckerman, Sophie
- Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Journal entriesMay 1849-March 1852 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
- Correspondence
  - To familyAugust 1849-51 (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  - From Sophie Tuckerman to family 1850-1852 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Biographical material (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - PassportMarch 13, 1852 (Box 1)
  - Book of pressed flowers circa 1822-40s (Box 1)
  - Account book of estate 1856 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - WillJanuary 1844 (Box 1)